<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>phylogenetics on Dominic J. Bennett</title>
    <link>/tags/phylogenetics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in phylogenetics on Dominic J. Bennett</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Dominic J. Bennett {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/phylogenetics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaius</title>
      <link>/software/gaius/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/gaius/</guid>
      <description>Divide and conquer phylogenetic supermatrices and supertrees in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>restez</title>
      <link>/software/restez/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/restez/</guid>
      <description>Create and Query a Local Copy of GenBank in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>phylotaR</title>
      <link>/software/phylotar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/phylotar/</guid>
      <description>Automated Retrieval of Orthologous DNA Sequences from GenBank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A roadmap for global synthesis of the plant tree of life</title>
      <link>/publication/eiserhardt-2018-roadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/eiserhardt-2018-roadmap/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>phylotaR: An automated pipeline for retrieving orthologous DNA sequences from GenBank in R</title>
      <link>/publication/bennett-2018-phylotar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bennett-2018-phylotar/</guid>
      <description>Access content Open-access!
Abstract: The exceptional increase in molecular DNA sequence data in open repositories is mirrored by an ever-growing interest among evolutionary biologists to harvest and use those data for phylogenetic inference. Many quality issues, however, are known and the sheer amount and complexity of data available can pose considerable barriers to their usefulness. A key issue in this domain is the high frequency of sequence mislabeling encountered when searching for suitable sequences for phylogenetic analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>restez: Create and Query a Local Copy of GenBank in R</title>
      <link>/publication/bennett-2018-restez/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bennett-2018-restez/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>treeman</title>
      <link>/software/treeman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/treeman/</guid>
      <description>An R package for manipulating phylogentic trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic factorization of compositional data yields lineage-level associations in microbiome datasets</title>
      <link>/publication/washburne-2017-phylogenetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/washburne-2017-phylogenetic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protecting free-living dormice: molecular identification of cestode parasites in captive dormice (Muscardinus avellanarius) destined for reintroduction</title>
      <link>/publication/peniche-2017-protecting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/peniche-2017-protecting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>treeman: an R package for efficient and intuitive manipulation of phylogenetic trees</title>
      <link>/publication/bennett-2017-treeman/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bennett-2017-treeman/</guid>
      <description>Access content Open-access!
Abstract:
BACKGROUND:
Phylogenetic trees are hierarchical structures used for representing the inter-relationships between biological entities. They are the most common tool for representing evolution and are essential to a range of fields across the life sciences. The manipulation of phylogenetic trees-in terms of adding or removing tips-is often performed by researchers not just for reasons of management but also for performing simulations in order to understand the processes of evolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pG-lt</title>
      <link>/software/pglt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/pglt/</guid>
      <description>phyloGenerator-lite: generate phylogenies, lightly, in python (2013)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EcoDataTools</title>
      <link>/software/ecodatatools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software/ecodatatools/</guid>
      <description>Tools for manipulating ecological data &amp;ndash; first ever R package! (2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis: Testing for Non-random Phylogenetic Responses to Urbanisation Using Mass Phylogeny Estimation (MPE)</title>
      <link>/publication/bennett-2013-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bennett-2013-testing/</guid>
      <description>Abstract: The phylogenetic approach in biodiversity science is an important and growing set of tools used for a wide range of questions and applications from conservation assessment to testing patterns in community assembly. Yet, with the dawn of the big data age, the size and scope of datasets in biology are becom ing ever larger thanks to revolutions in information technology, increased data sharing, &amp;lsquo;big data&amp;rsquo; initiatives and online repositories. Although such sources promise biodiversity analyses at an unprecedentedly large scale, there is no clear solution on how to similarly upscale the phylogenetic approach.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>